Guide to the William Stanley Braithwaite Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Stanley Braithwaite Papers
1797-1942
1830-1942
JWJ MSS 72
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(5 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
The William Stanley Braithwaite Papers document his personal and professional life and span the dates 1797 to 1942. The Papers contain correspondence, writings, and other papers, which provide evidence of Braithwaite's career as a writer, publisher, and anthologist. The Papers also includes third-party correspondence, notably, a letter from Sir Joseph Banks to J. Nicol from circa 1797.
Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Walter R. Benjamin and Margaret Carpenter on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund, 2003 and from William Reese Company on the Danford N. Barney, Jr. Fund, 1991.
The addition was purchased from Southpaw Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2015.
Other material came to the library in small quantities from various sources as indicated on individual folders.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are microfilmed, as noted on individual folders.
William Stanley Beaumont Braithwaite (1878-1962)
William Stanley Braithwaite was born in Boston, December 6, 1878, to William Smith Braithwaite and Emma DeWolf. He led a difficult life as a child of two mixed race parents and due to the death of his father in 1886, he left school early and joined the workforce at the age of twelve. His first employment was fortuitous; he was apprenticed in a Boston publishing house where he was exposed to the works of John Keats. Braithwaite acquired a passion for romantic poetry which drew him to a literary life. In 1903 he married Emma Kelly with whom he had seven children. Following his marriage, he committed himself even more intensely to his literary career, and completed and published his first volume of poetry, Lyrics of Life and Love (1904). He traveled to New York City in search of a career in journalism, but encountered an unfamiliar atmosphere of racial prejudice and soon returned to Boston where he found employment in 1906 as a critic and reviewer for The Boston Evening Transcript. While at The Transcript he published his first anthologies as collections of the year's best poetry. In 1908 he completed his best-known work of poetry, The House of Falling Leaves, in which he explored the development of African-American writing in the U.S. He attempted to start up his own literary publication, The Poetic Journal and a publishing house, B.J. Brimmer, which he founded with fellow poet Winifred Virginia Jackson. Both ventures proved unsuccessful and Braithwaite was beset with financial difficulties. In 1935, after having received several honorary degrees he was offered a professorship at Atlanta University which he held until 1945. Braithwaite returned to New York City and completed his final collection of poems, Selected Poems, in 1948 and remained there until his death on June 8, 1962.
Scope and Contents
The William Stanley Braithwaite Papers document his personal and professional life and span the dates 1797 to 1942. The Papers contain correspondence, writings, and other papers, which provide evidence of Braithwaite's career as a writer, publisher, and anthologist.
Braithwaite's correspondence records his professional and, to a lesser degree, personal relationships. Correspondents include poets such as Stephen Vincent Benét, William Rose Benét, Witter Bynner, Sarah Norcliffe Cleghorn, Grace Hazard Conkling, Olive Tilford Dargan, Rebecca Harding Davis, John Gould Fletcher, Georgia Douglas Johnson, James Weldon Johnson, James Joyce, Joyce Kilmer, Aline Murray Kilmer, Vachel Lindsay, Philip Ainsworth Means, and Louis Untermeyer. Other correspondents include W.E.B. DuBois and George E. Haynes. The correspondence series also contains third-party correspondence; notably, a letter from Sir Joseph Banks to J. Nicol from circa1797.
Proofs, clippings of articles, and publicity materials represent Braithwaite's career as an anthologist and as an author for The Boston Evening Transcript. Other papers document his work as a publisher (with B.J. Brimmer) and lecturer. The papers also contain a portrait and a photograph of Braithwaite as well as his collection of autographs.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, circa 1797, 1877-1942. II. Writings, 1908-1928. III. Other Papers, 1830-1935, undated. IV. Addition, 1911-1935.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; African American critics -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962
- Correspondence, circa 1797, 1877-1942; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: William Stanley Braithwaite Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence dating from 1797 to 1942 documenting Braithwaite's career. The correspondence provides insight into Braithwaite's relationships with authors and pertains to his work as a critic and anthologist. There are numerous letters between Braithwaite and authors regarding his anthologies. In their letters correspondents often grant permission to Braithwaite to include their pieces in his anthologies and some authors enclose copies of their poems and details regarding last minute changes to their writing (such as edits to a particular poem and justifications for such changes). Braithwaite also corresponded extensively with Arthur Upson's mother Mrs. Julia Upson and fiancée Ruth Shepard Phelps following Upson's death in 1908. Correspondents include: Stephen Vincent Benét, William Rose Benét, Witter Bynner, Sarah Norcliffe Cleghorn, Grace Hazard Conkling, Olive Tilford Dargan, Rebecca Harding Davis, William E. B. DuBois, John Gould Fletcher, George E. Haynes, Georgia Douglas Johnson, James Weldon Johnson, James Joyce, Joyce and Aline Murray Kilmer, Vachel Lindsay, Philip Ainsworth Means, and Louis Untermeyer.
  The series also includes third-party correspondence such as a letter from Sir Joseph Banks to J. Nicol and correspondence between Frederick A. Kent and various government officials. Braithwaite's correspondence with Rebecca Harding Davis includes correspondence with Mary Allen and other third-parties. Braithwaite collected autographs so it is possible that some of the third-party correspondence reflects this pursuit. Braithwaite's autograph collection is in Series III.
  - William Stanley Braithwaite Correspondence
    - General "Adams-Arden", 1896-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General "Baker-Byles", 1897-1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Benét, Stephen Vincent, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Benét, William Rose, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Branch, Anna H., 1905-1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      To: 0 / From: 3
    - Brooks, Edmund D., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes clippings re: Arthur Upson
    - Bynner, Witter, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General "Cabell-Crawford", 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Church, Robert R., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Letter from B. J. Brimmer Co.
    - Cleghorn, Sarah Norcliffe, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Colcord, Lincoln, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Conkling, Grace Hazard, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General "Da-Dz", 1898-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Daly, Thomas Augustine, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Dargan, Olive Tilford, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Davis, Rebecca Harding, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes correspondence between Rebecca Harding Davis and Mary Allen.
    - Delta Phi Delta, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      To: 1 / From: 0
    - Dodson, Owen, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      To: 0 / From: 1
    - DuBois, William E. B., 1918, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes letter from B. J. Brimmer Co.
      To: 1 / From: 1
    - General "Ea-Ez", 1891-1914 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Edgett, Edwin F., 1908-23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      To: 17 / From: 0
    - Evans, Donald, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - General "Fa-Fz", 1906-1910 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fletcher, John Gould, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - General "Ga-Gz", 1877-1932 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - G. Bell & Sons, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - George Allen & Sons, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - General "Ha-Hz", 1910-1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hagedorn, Hermann, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hale, R. T., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Haynes, George E., 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      To: 10 / From: 3
    - General "Ia-Jz", 1910 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Jackman, Harold, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Johnson, Georgia Douglas, 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Includes two poems and correspondence regarding Georgia Douglas Johnson
      To: 1 / From: 3
    - Johnson, James Weldon, 1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Includes miscellaneous material regarding James Weldon Johnson
      To: 2 / From: 2
    - Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Joyce, James, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - General "Ka-Kz", 1910-1932 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Kilmer, Aline Murray, 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Mr. King, 1911 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - General "La-Lz", 1885-1918 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Le Gallienne, Richard, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Lewis, Sinclair, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Lindsay, Vachel, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1890-1912 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - General "Ma-Mz", 1890-1932 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - MacKaye, Percy, 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Malone, Walter, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Means, Philip Ainsworth, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Mitchell, Ruth Comfort, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - General "Na-Nz", 1910-1921 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - General "Oa-Oz", 1910-1919 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - General "Pa-Pz", 1897-1932 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Peabody, Josephine Preston, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Percy, William Alexander, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Phelps, Ruth Shepard, 1908-25 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      To: 6 / From: 0
    - Phelps, ------, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      To: 0 / From: 4
    - "Punch" proprietors, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - General "Ra-Rz", 1910-1920 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Reese, Lizette Woodworth, 1917-1921 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Rittenhouse, Jessie E., undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Includes draft of introduction by WSB
      To: 2 / From: 0
    - Robinson, Corrine Roosevelt, 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1915-1920 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Roth, Samuel, 1918 Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - General "Sa-Sz", 1910-1932 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Smith, Elder & co., publishers, London, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Sprague, Charles, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Sterling, George, 1912-1915 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Stephens, Wallace, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Stork, Charles Wharton, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - General "Ta-Tz", 1910-1919 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Teasdale, Sara, 1915-1920 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Torrence, Ridgely, 1916-1918 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Untermeyer, Louis, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Unwin, T. Fisher, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Upson, Arthur, 1906, 1908, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
      Includes three poems by Upson and correspondence regarding Upson
      To: 8 / From: 0
    - Upson, Julia, 1908-11, undated (Box 2, Folder 79-80)
      To: 29 / From: 0
    - Van Dyke, Henry, 1912-34 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      Includes correspondence with Teritius Van Dyke
      To: 3 / From: 1
    - Viking Press, 1927, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - General "Wa-Wz", 1909-1918 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Wattles, Willard, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1886-1914 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Wood, Clement, 1921-30 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      Includes correspondence regarding Clement Wood
      To: 6 / From: 5
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - Banks, Sir Joseph to J. Nicol, circa 1797 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Goodspeed's Book Shop, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Contains correspondence with Donald Wing regarding the Beinecke Library's purchase of Braithwaite's correspondence
    - Kent, Frederick A., 1890-1913 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      Contains correspondence from Samuel W. McCall, Henry E. Burnham, Jacob H. Gallinger, and other government officials
- Writings, 1908-1928; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  The series contains extensive publicity material for Braithwaite's writing projects, both as an anthologist and a journalist. Braithwaite's career with the The Boston Evening Transcript is reflected in the various clippings of his writings (loose and as part of a scrapbook) from the newspaper dating from 1916 to 1924. The series also includes page proofs for The Book of Victorian Verse and a handwritten list of permissions for an anthology.
  - Anthology of Magazine Verse, publicity material, 1914-1928 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - "The Best Books of the Year," The Boston Evening Transcript, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - The Book of Victorian Verse, page proofs, 1909 November (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Christmas Books for Children, reprinted from the The Boston Evening Transcript, circa 1913 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Cornhill Company publicity material, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - "An Improving Product and an Improving Public Taste," The Boston Evening Transcript, 1912 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Our Lady's Choir, publicity material, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - "Sculptured Worship," poem, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - The Wounded Eros by W.W. Gibson, introduction by Braithwaite, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Scrapbook of various articles from The Boston Evening Transcript, 1916-1924 (Box Oversize Box 4, Folder 99-100)
  - Loose clippings removed from The Boston Evening Transcript scrapbook, 1916-1924 (Box 101 (Broadside)–102 (Broadside))
  - List of permissions for an anthology, undated (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
    Material missing since 1996
- Other Papers, 1830-1935, undated; Series III
  Other Papers contains material that provides evidence of Braithwaite's career as a publisher, with the B.J. Brimmer Company, and as a lecturer. The series also includes Braithwaite's autograph collection, a portrait, and a photograph of Braithwaite.
  - B.J. Brimmer Company publicity material, circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - "Braithwaite's Course on the Theory and Practice of Verse," publicity material, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Lecture series, publicity material, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Memo with Braithwaite's addresses, undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Autograph collection and citizenship paper, 1830-1894 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Portrait of Braithwaite by K.B., undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Photograph of Braithwaite, undated (Box 3, Folder 111)
- Addition, 1911-1935; Series IV; 0.21
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Southpaw Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2015. Vendor lis is filed at the beginning of the series.
  The addition contains correspondence, writings, and printed material relating to William Stanley Braithwaite.
  The series is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Printed Material.
  - Correspondence, 1929-1934
    - Boie, Mildred, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 112)
      Concerns Boie's request for Braithwaite to send a letter to Mrs. Edward McDowell of the McDowell Colony on behalf of Boie. Enclosed is a typescript draft short story by Boie, entitled "Cold Countries", clippings of writings by Boie, and Braithwaite's draft to McDowell
    - Davis, Edwards, 1934 July 28 and August 27 (Box 5, Folder 113)
      Includes typescript and typescript carbon drafts of opinions by others on Davis's Lovers Of Life: An Epic Biography Of A Soul.
    - Library of Congress. Copyright Office, includes copyright registration form and application, 1934 July 12 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Mason, Francis, 1929 August 16 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Mooney, Tom, 1934 May 7 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Writings, 1915, undated
    - Untitled holograph draft of a review or comment on a book concerning paralysis caused by fear, undated (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Untitled holograph draft on "the place of the Negro race in American life", undated (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Printed Material, 1911-1935
    - Copyright and dedication pages from proof of Anthology of Magazine Verse for 1914 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Proofs, fragments, corrected, of Anthology of Magazine Poetry for 1915 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Printed card for B. J. Brimmer Company, Publishers, announcing an upcoming office relocation, undated (Box 5, Folder 121)
      Braithwaite was president of the company
    - Booklet, "Coming Home and Goodbye by E. Sewell Hill" with a forward referring to Braithwaite's "The Poet and the Magazines" in Boston Transcript, December 9, 1911., undated (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Printed postcard from Cornhill Company, Publishers that mentions Braithwaite, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Promotional brochure and order form for Braithwaite's Sandy Star, A Book of Poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Reproduction of a drawing of Braithwaite, undated (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Brochure for lectures by Braithwaite, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 126)